<page xmlns="http://www.gnome.org/~shaunm/mallard"
       id="mal_em">
<info>
  <link type="guide" xref="mal_inline"/>
  <link type="seealso" xref="mal_attr_link"/>

  <credit type="author">
    <name>Shaun McCance</name>
    <email>shaunm@gnome.org</email>
  </credit>
  <copyright>
    <year>2008</year>
    <name>Shaun McCance</name>
  </copyright>

  <version number="0.1" date="2008-02-19" status="incomplete"/>
</info>

<title>Emphasis</title>

<synopsis><code mime="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax">
mal_inline_em = element em {
  <link xref="mal_attr_link">mal_attr_link</link> ?,
  <link xref="mal_inline#simple">mal_inline__simple</link>
}
</code></synopsis>

<p>The <code>em</code> element indicates that its enclosed text should be
emphasized.  You may use <code>em</code> to stress certain words in a sentence.
Do not use <code>em</code> to effect a particular typographic style, since it
may be rendered differently by different processing tools.</p>


<!-- BEGIN examples -->
<section id="examples">
  <title>Examples</title>
  <comment>
    <cite date="2008-02-19"><name>Shaun McCance</name></cite>
    <p>Add examples.</p>
  </comment>
</section>
<!-- END examples -->


<!-- BEGIN processing -->
<section id="processing">
  <title>Processing Expectations</title>
  <p>Emphasized text is traditionally presented in an italic or oblique font.
  Italic and oblique fonts stress a portion of text without making it stand
  out.  By contrast, bold text tends to draw the eye, which can be distracting
  when reading long passages of text.  In scripts without a distinction between
  roman and italic type styles, it may still be possible to use an oblique font
  or some other font variation.  Bold text may be used if necessary.</p>
  <p>Underlining should be avoided completely, since it hurts the legibility
  of the text.  This problem is especially pronounced in scripts which place
  diacritical marks below the text.  In these scripts, underlining can render
  the text completely illegible.</p>
</section>
<!-- END processing -->


<!-- BEGIN docbook -->
<section id="docbook">
  <title>Comparison to DocBook</title>
  <p>The <code>em</code> element is functionally similar to the
  <code href="http://www.docbook.org/tdg/en/html/emphasis.html">emphasis</code>
  element in DocBook.  Athough DocBook does not normatively specify a means of
  controlling the presentation, most DocBook processing tools allow writers to
  set the <code>role</code> attribute to <code>bold</code> or <code>strong</code>
  to specify bold text.  We explicitly recommend against doing this in Mallard
  documents and processing tools.</p>
</section>
<!-- END docbook -->

</page>
