<page xmlns="http://www.gnome.org/~shaunm/mallard"
      type="topic"
      id="mal_page">

<info>
  <version number="0.1" date="2008-02-21" status="stub"/>
</info>

<title>Pages</title>

<synopsis><code mime="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax">
namespace local = ""
default namespace mal = "http://www.gnome.org/~shaunm/mallard"
start = mal_page
mal_page = element page {
  attribute id { xsd:ID },
  attribute type { "guide" | "topic"} ?,
  attribute style { xsd:NMTOKENS } ?,
  attribute * - (mal:* | local:*) { text } *,

  <link xref="mal_info">mal_info</link> ?,
  <link xref="mal_block_title">mal_block_title</link>,
  <link xref="mal_block">mal_block</link> *,
  <link xref="mal_section">mal_section</link> *
}
</code></synopsis>

<p>The <code>page</code> element is the root element of any Mallard page file.
In Mallard, documents are composed of discrete pages which are  interlinked
using various linking mechanisms.  There are two types of pages in Mallard:
<link xref="#guide">guide pages</link> and <link xref="#topic">topic pages</link>.
Topic pages contain the bulk of the material discussed in a document, whereas
guide pages serve as navigational aids.</p>


<!-- BEGIN notes -->
<section id="notes">
  <title>Notes</title>
  <list>
    <item><p>The <code>page</code> element contains an optional
    <code xref="mal_info">info</code> element, a <code xref="mal_block_title">title</code>
    element, any <link xref="mal_block">general block content</link>, and
    any number of <code xref="mal_section">section</code> elements.</p></item>

    <item><p>The <code>page</code> element is the top-level element in any
    Mallard page file, and cannot occur in any other elements.</p></item>

    <item><p>The <code>id</code> attribute takes a unique identifier, which
    should match the base file name (without extension) of the file containing
    the page.</p></item>

    <item><p>The <code>type</code> attribute takes the values <code>"guide"</code> and
    <code>"topic"</code>.  <link xref="#guide">Guide pages</link> and <link xref="#topic">topic
    pages</link> are discussed below.  If the <code>type</code> attribute is
    omitted, it is assumed to be <code>"topic"</code>.</p></item>

    <item><p>The <code>style</code> attribute takes a space-separated list of
    style hints.  Processing tools should adjust their behavior according to
    those style hints they understand.</p></item>

    <item><p>The <code>page</code> element can have attributes from external
    namespaces.  See <link xref="mal_external"/> for more information
    on external-namespace attributes.</p></item>
  </list>
</section>
<!-- END notes -->


<!-- BEGIN guide -->
<section id="guide">
  <title>Guide Pages</title>

  <p>Guide pages have the <code>type</code> attribute set to
  <code>"guide"</code>.  They serve as navigational aids, linking to topics and
  other guides.  Readers can can browse through guides much as they would browse
  through container sections in a linear document.  Since page can be included
  in multiple guides, however, readers are able to reach the same content by
  navigating different paths.</p>

  <p>Guide pages have links automatically inserted into their content based
  on topic links within their own <code xref="mal_info">info</code> elements
  and guide links within the <code>info</code> elements of other pages and
  sections.  Guide pages can contain sections to help organize content.  Each
  section in a guide page has automatic links inserted as well.  See
  <link xref="links#topic"/> for details on automatic topic links.</p>

  <p>Guides also have see also links generated automatically.  See
  <link xref="links#seealso"/> for more information.</p>

  <p>Generally, guide pages will contain some introductory content to help
  readers understand the topics being presented.  Introductory content should
  be short and concise.</p>
</section>
<!-- END topic -->


<!-- BEGIN topic -->
<section id="topic">
  <title>Topic Pages</title>

  <p>Topic pages have the <code>type</code> attribute set to
  <code>"topic"</code>, or have no <code>type</code> attribute at all.  Topics
  contain the bulk of the material in a document.  A Topic may be a tutorial,
  a conceptual overview, reference material, or any other type of content.
  Mallard does not distinguish between different content types, although tools
  may introduce special styling based on style hints.  Topics are distinguished
  from guides only in that their primary purpose is to convey information,
  whereas guides serve as navigational aids.</p>

  <p>Topic pages have links automatically inserted to all guides which link
  to them.  Topic pages can contain sections to help organize material and
  present finer-grained chunks of information to the reader.  Each section
  in a topic page has automatic guide links inserted as well.  See
  <link xref="links#guide"/> for details on automatic guide links.</p>

  <p>Topics also have see also links generated automatically.  See
  <link xref="links#seealso"/> for more information.</p>
</section>
<!-- END topic -->


<!-- BEGIN processing -->
<section id="processing">
  <title>Processing Expectations</title>
</section>
<!-- END processing -->

</page>
