<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<page xmlns="http://www.gnome.org/~shaunm/mallard"
      type="topic"
      id="mal_inline_app">

<info>
  <link type="guide" xref="mal_inline#elements"/>

  <version number="0.1" date="2007-02-08" status="review"/>

  <desc>The <code>app</code> element marks the human-readable name of an
  application or the title of a window within an application.</desc>

  <credit type="author">
    <name>Shaun McCance</name>
    <email>shaunm@gnome.org</email>
  </credit>
  <copyright>
    <year>2007</year>
    <name>Shaun McCance</name>
  </copyright>

  <include href="legal.xml" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
</info>

<title>Application Names</title>

<synopsis><code mime="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax">
mal_inline_app = element app {
  <link xref="mal_attr_link">mal_attr_link</link> ?,
  attribute style { xsd:NMTOKENS } ?,
  attribute * - (mal:* | local:*) { text } *,

  <link xref="mal_inline">mal_inline</link>+
}
</code></synopsis>

<p>The <code>app</code> element marks the human-readable name of an application
or the title of a window within an application.  It should not be used to mark
the name of the command used to run an application; use
<code xref="mal_inline_cmd">cmd</code> for this purpose instead.</p>


<!-- BEGIN notes -->
<section id="notes">
  <title>Notes</title>
  <list type="bullet">
    <item><p>The <code>style</code> attribute takes a space-seperated list of
    style hints.  Processing tools should adjust their rendering according to
    those style hints they understand.</p></item>

    <item><p>The <code>app</code> element can link to other pages or documents.
    See <link xref="mal_attr_link"/> for more information.</p></item>
  </list>
  <comment><cite date="2008-11-13"><name>Shaun McCance</name></cite>
  <p>Add a note about external attributes</p></comment>
</section>
<!-- END notes -->


<!-- BEGIN processing -->
<section id="processing">
  <title>Processing Expectations</title>

  <p>Application names are usually nouns, and are often common words or phrases
  that are indicative of their functionality.  Frequently, they are simply the
  name of what the application is.  In English and many other languages, the
  use of an application name in a sentence may sound like the author has simply
  mistakenly omitted an article, if the application name is not understood to
  be a title.</p>

  <p>For example, the calculator application that comes with Gnome is called
  <app>Calculator</app>.  If an author were to write <quote>To start
  Calculator…</quote>, then a reader may confuse this for <quote>To
  start the calculator…</quote> with an error.  This is even more pronounced
  in languages such as German where nouns are always capitalized.</p>

  <p>For this reason, it is recommended that application names marked with the
  <code>app</code> element are rendered in italics or using some other font
  variation.</p>
</section>
<!-- END processing -->


<!-- BEGIN docbook -->
<section id="docbook">
  <title>Comparison to DocBook</title>
  <p>The <code>app</code> element is functionally similar to DocBook's
  <code href="http://www.docbook.org/tdg/en/html/application.html">application</code>
  element.</p>
</section>
<!-- END docbook -->

</page>
